Finding Aid for Ali A. Mazrui papers, 1959-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings by Mazrui
  - "Tom Mboya, Underdevelopment, and I," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Tools of Africa's Exploitation: A Triple Heritage of Technology,", typescript (Box 5)
    (draft of chapter for The Africans (book), 1986)
  - "Towards a New International Order: From the Ethics of Charity to the Economics of Justice," conference proceedings May 1976, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards a New International Religious Order," conference paper May 1979, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards a Political Meteorology," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards a Shared Humanity," book chapter undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards Decolonizing Modernity: Education and Culture Conflict in Eastern Africa," Mazrui and Teshome Wagaw undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards Democratizing the Study of History: An African Case-Study," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards Institutionalizing Human Rights: An African Perspective," background paper for UN Symposium June-July 1980, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards Oil Power and the Political Resurrection of Islam," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards Re-Africanizing Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - 'Towards the Impeachment of African Presidents: Some Preliminary Thoughts," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Towards the Year 2000 Identity and the Future of Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Trial of Christopher Okigbo,", typescript (Box 5)
    (excerpt from novel of same name by Mazrui pub. 1971)
  - "Types of Political Theory Research: Normative and Empirical," research note August 1965, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Uganda: Transition and After," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Uganda's Isolationism: From Tom Mboya to Julius K. Nyerere," 1979, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Uganda's Political Achievements," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Uncle Sam's Hearing Aid: Uncomfortable America in a Turbulent World," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Underdevelopment and the Undergraduate: Two Philosophies of University Education," January 1970, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Ungovernability of Political Units: Elusive Legitimacy in Africa's Political Experience," Mazrui and Victor Olorunsola, conference paper August 1976, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The University of East Africa as a Political Institution," Mazrui and Yash Tandon undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Utilisation of Collective Anger in Consensus Formation in East Africa," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Violation of Human Rights in Uganda: Is It a Case for International Sanctions?" prepared for US Congressional hearings, February 1978, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Violence in Contemporary Black Africa: The Causes, the Consequences, and the Quest for Solutions," with various related articles March 1975, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Violence in Uganda: Is It Religious, Ethnic or 'Lebanese'?" undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Violent Change and Emergent Empathy," book chapter undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Violent Change and Receding Empathy," book chapter undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The War Mystique in Contemporary Cultures," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "The Warrior Tradition and the Masculinity of War," (Box 5)
  - "Was Jesus A Coloured Man?" July 1972, typescript (Box 5)
  - "When is Investment Foreign?" undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Women as Warriors: An African Perspective," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Women, Power and War" conference paper June 1975, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Women's Liberation, Nuclear Proliferation and the War Mystique in Contemporary Cultures," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "World Dimensions of the Community of Black Peoples: The Case of Education and Culture Conflict in Eastern Africa," Mazrui and Teshome Wagaw, conference paper December 1980 (Box 5)
  - "The World Economy and the African-Afroamerican Connection," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "World Futures: Which Ways Are Forward?" conference paper November 1978, typescript (Box 5)
  - "World Order Through World Culture: An African Perspective," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "World Reform and the Imperative of Mobility," undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Zimbabwe: Democracy Under Strain?" undated, typescript (Box 5)
  - "Zionism and Apartheid: Strange Bedfellows or Natural Allies,", typescript (Box 5)
    (revised version of paper to be published in Alternatives, November 1982)
- Materials Related to "The Africans" TV series (1986)
  The Materials Related to "The Africans" Television Series series (1.0 linear feet) consists of public relations materials, reviews, news articles, correspondence, and photographs about the series, produced jointly by the BBC and PBS and broadcast in Britain, the United States, and elsewhere in 1986 and subsequently. Original folder headings are retained, and may not be complete or accurate.
  - Ann Arbor News (Box 6)
  - Exhibit Materials (Box 6)
  - Items With Missing Info (Box 6)
  - Promotional Material (Box 6)
  - Reviews -- The Africans -- National Endowment of the Humanities (Box 6)
  - Reviews -- The Africans TV Documentary Series, 14 folders (Box 6)
  - Reviews -- The Africans TV Documentary Series -- Letters to the Editor (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- Addresses, Essays, Lectures (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- News Articles, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- Photos (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- Program Guides (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- Questionnaire Results (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- TV Listings, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- University Course (Box 6)
  - The Africans -- Viewers' Response (Box 6)
  - The Africans (TV Doc. Series) -- Transcripts (Box 6)
  - Book Listings -- The Africans (Box 6)
  - Books -- Reviews -- The Africans (Box 6)
  - Books -- Reviews -- The Africans (Box 6)
- Biographical
  The Biographical series (0.5 linear feet) consists of files of biographical information, bibliographies and curricula vitae, and interviews with and news articles about Mazrui. News coverage is primarily from the 1980s, focusing on Mazrui's "The Africans" television series and his comments on international relations issues.
  - Mazrui Bibliography (Box 7)
  - Mazrui Biographical Materials (Box 7)
  - Mazrui Biographical Materials (Box 7)
  - Mazrui CV (Box 7)
  - Interviews with Mazrui, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - News Coverage of Mazrui, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Awards and Honors (Box 7)
  - Reviews of Work by Mazrui, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Subject Files 1979-1989
  The Subject Files (1979-1989) series (0.5 linear feet) consists of Mazrui's files of clippings and articles about current events topics, primarily containing material produced during the 1980s. Folder labels are primarily the original labels. Folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - Acquired Immune Deficiency (Box 7)
  - Afro-Americans (Box 7)
  - Afro-Guyanese (Box 7)
  - Announcements (Box 7)
  - Authors, African (Box 7)
  - Black Diplomacy and Comparative Black Experience (Box 7)
  - Career (Box 7)
  - Civil Rights (Box 7)
  - Democracy (Box 7)
  - Economic Assistance, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Education (Box 7)
  - Education, Higher (Box 7)
  - History, African, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Human Rights Conference (Box 7)
  - Institute of Black World (Box 7)
  - International Relations, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Israel (Box 7)
  - Kenya -- Social Reform (Box 7)
  - Leadership (Box 7)
  - Notes and Letters (Box 7)
  - Nuclear Weapons -- Africa (Box 7)
  - Nuclear Weapons -- Afro-Americans (Box 7)
  - Nuclear Weapons -- Muslims (Box 7)
  - Philosophy, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Political Participation (Box 7)
  - Political Science, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Religion (Box 7)
  - Satanic Verses (Box 7)
  - Socialism (Box 7)
  - Student Activism (Box 7)
  - South Africa (Box 7)
  - Tanzania -- Self-Reliance (Box 7)
  - Underdeveloped Areas, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (2.0 linear feet) consists of Mazrui's professional and some personal correspondence beginning in the 1950s and continuing through his tenure at the University of Michigan. Folder headings are the original headings. In some cases original folders or binders did not have headings. Folders are arranged chronologically by the first year covered in the folder.
  - Professional 1959-1963 (Box 8)
  - BBC Contracts 1963 (Box 8)
  - College Forms and Documents 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - Lectures, Seminars and Talks 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - Mombasa Affairs 1963-1964 (Box 8)
  - African Studies Association 1963-1971 (Box 8)
  - Makerere 1965 (Box 8)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Conferences, Seminars and Lectures 1965-1967 (Box 8)
  - Mazrui Correspondence 1966 (Box 8)
  - Makerere 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Confidential Letters, Prof. 1966-1976 (Box 8)
  - Mazrui Correspondence 1967 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence with Diplomats 1967-1971 (Box 8)
  - Language 1968 (Box 8)
  - Mazrui Correspondence 1968 (Box 8)
  - International Sociological Association 1968-1972 (Box 8)
  - 1969 (Box 8)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 8)
  - 1970 (Box 9)
  - Chapters Elsewhere 1970 (Box 9)
  - Violence and Thought 1970 (Box 9)
  - African Conferences 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - Annual Reports 1971-1972 (Note: Makerere personnel reports -- May CONTAIN CONFIDENTIAL PERSONAL INFORMATION) (Box 9)
  - Australia Trip & Austria 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - Lectures Abroad 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - Molly's Committees (Mazrui's wife Molly Mazrui) 1971-1972 (Box 9)
  - Comments on Mazrui Writings 1972 (Box 9)
  - Editorial Roles 1972 (Box 9)
  - International African Institute 1972 (Box 9)
  - Mazrui Chapters Elsewhere 1972 (Box 9)
  - Meeting of International African Institute/Open Society Conference, Villa Serbelloni, Italy 1972 (Box 9)
  - Publicity 1972 (Box 9)
  - Lectures in Quebec and Davidson 1972 (Box 9)
  - Mazrui Correspondence (Professional) 1981-1989 (Box 9)
  - Newspapers 1980-1985 (Box 9)
- Teaching Materials
  The Teaching Materials series (0.3 linear feet) consists of materials about African studies programs in the United States, reading assignments for courses taught by Mazrui, and related notes.
  - Materials on African Studies Programs (Box 10)
  - African studies materials (Box 10)
  - Reading assignments for African/African-American studies courses, 2 folders (Box 10)
    (courses, dates not specified)
- Scholarly materials
  The Scholarly Materials series (0.3 linear feet) consists of peer reviews by Mazrui of other scholars' work, administrative materials from scholarly organizations including the International Congress of Africanists and the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies at the University of Michigan, and miscellaneous other scholarly materials.
  - Language and Command (Box 10)
  - Mss of Opoku Agyeman, The Osagyefo: Patterns of Kwame Nkrumah's Impact on East Africa, with introduction by Mazrui (Box 10)
  - Reviews of others' work (Box 10)
  - Notes from UC Berkeley Economics Course undated (Box 10)
  - International Congress of Africanists December 1967 (Box 10)
- Clippings
  The Clippings series (0.3 linear feet) consists of articles, clippings and whole newspapers preserved by Mazrui on various African topics. The series is retained in the original folder groupings, which were undated and had no headings.
  - Center for Afro-American and African Studies materials (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings-Uganda (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Published Materials
  The Published Materials series (0.5 linear feet) consists of periodicals, most produced in Africa, collected by Mazrui. Runs are incomplete and sporadic. Periodicals collected include Africa and West Africa.
  - Africa, May and June, 1975 (Box 11)
  - West Africa, scattered issues, 1961-62, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Survival, July/August 1978Adelphia Papers Nos. 144, 145, September 1977 AF Press Clips, May-June 1975 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 2 folders (Box 11)
- Writings by Others
  The Writings by Others series (1.5 linear feet) consists of scholarly papers by writers other than Mazrui, primarily prepared for presentation at academic conferences. The largest groups of these are papers from the "1970 Universities of East Africa Social Science Conference" (47 folders) and the University of Guyana International Conference, (37 folders).
  - Barnum, H.N., "Reducing Mortality When Diseases Are Interdependent," Center for Research on Economic Development, University of Michigan August 1978 (Box 11)
  - E. African Institute of Social Research Conference Papers January 1965 (Box 11)
  - Consultative Meeting on Language Planning Processes Papers, East-West Center April 1979 (Box 11)
  - Independent States and Interdependent Societies Colloquium, Bellagio, Italy April 1968 (Box 11)
  - International Political Science Association Louvain Round Table Papers September 1971 (Box 11)
  - International Political Science Association Louvain Round Table Papers September 1971 (Box 11)
  - Physical Education with A Military Bias and Discipline (Box 11)
    (undated handwritten mss., no author name)
  - Rwabuhungu, T., "Analysis of conflicts and revelation of character in the 'Odour of Chrysanthemums' by D.H. Lawrence," undated, handwritten mss (Box 11)
  - Tropical African Studies Conference Papers, Ibadan April 1964 (Box 11)
  - Universities Social Sciences Council Conference Papers, Makerere undated, typescripts (Box 11)
  - 1970 Universities of East Africa Social Science Conference Papers, December 1970, 47 folders (Box 12)
  - University of Guyana International Conference Papers July 1988, 37 folders (Box 12)
Related Material
Records of the Center for Afroamerican and African Studies at the University of Michigan, where Mazrui taught from 1974 to 1989 and served as director from 1978-1981, are also held by the Bentley Historical Library.